JALE: Well, as it turns out, I’m a victim from the floods in La Iguaná,
Jale: Bueno, resulta que yo soy damnificada de la inundación de Iguaná,
since 1988, so…I used to have a photo album with all my family, all my children,
en 1988. Yo tenía el álbum de mi familia, de todos mis hijos,
Now I just have these little memories of them.
Ahora solo tengo estos recuerditos de ellos.
This is my eldest, Silvia Iris,
Esta es mi hija mayor, Silvia Iris,
this is Luis Guillermo,
este es Luis Guillermo,
and this is Diego Alejandro.
y este es Diego Alejandro.
When he was little, he…he thought what I did was awful,
Cuando él estaba pequeño... le parecía horrible…
what I shouted in the street, because I said,
lo que yo gritaba en la calle:
I shouted “here comes the black lady with the white, powdery thingy”.
lo que yo grito: “Llegó la Negra con la cosa blanca y empolvada.”
Well, you know kids don’t get it. And one time I took him to get a haircut,
Usted sabe… ¡Uno entiende a los chicos! Una vez lo llevé al peluquero,
when the kids came and they were like “Jale, Jale, here’s Jale!”
Cuando llegaron los niños. " Jale, Jale, aquí está la Jale”
And they were all happy, and they kissed me,
¡Estaban felices! Me daban besitos... Contentos...
and they asked him “Diego, is Jale your mom?”
Le preguntaron: "Diego, ¿ la Jale es tu mamá?"
And he goes “No, she’s my aunt”.
Y dice: "No, ella es mi tía."
When he said that, I felt the earth opening up and swallowing me,
Cuando ese niño dijo eso yo sentí que la tierra se abría y me tragaba.
because I said “My God, I support my kids with this, I support my family with this, I provide for my home with this."
Porque yo decía: “Dios mío, con esto mantengo mis hijos, mantengo a mi familia, sustento mi hogar…”
"And this kid’s denying who I am. I work so hard to support them…”
“y este niño, ¿Me niega? Porque yo trabajo tan duro para mantenerlos a ellos.”
And, well…I said “I’m not paying attention to this”.
Y bueno... me dije que no prestaría atención a eso.
JALE: People in the street ask me “You don’t have any problems, Jale, do you?”
Jale: Me preguntan en la calle: "¿Cierto Jale que usted no tiene problemas?"
“You don’t feel a thing, right?”
"¿Usted no siente nada?"
“You laugh all the time, you dance all the time, you shout all the time…”
“Usted siempre riéndose, bailando, gritando…”
But the pain goes inside, sweetie. The pain goes inside.
Pero las penas van por dentro mi'hija. ¡Las penas van por dentro!
Because if we all cry, who’s gonna comfort us?
Porque si todos lloramos, ¿Quién nos consuela?
JALE: My only worry…among so many.
Jale: Mi única preocupación... ¡Entre tantas!
Because all of us have worries. We all have problems, like they say.
Porque todos tenemos preocupaciones, todos tenemos problemas...
But my main worry, most importantly, is what’s going to happen once I’m old.
Pero mi preocupación fundamental es ¿Qué va a pasar en mi vejez?
When my body stops being able to do anything, not even shouting.
cuando mi cuerpo no pueda hacer nada. Ni siquiera gritar "Jale".
No more black lady with the white thingy, or black, or purple.
Ni llegó la Negra con la cosa blanca, ni con la cosa negra, ni con la cosa morada.
Only with the tired thingy.
Sino con la cosa cansada.
JALE: That’s difficult. Very difficult. Work is hard.
Esto es muy duro. ¡El trabajo es muy duro!
Very hard, because this is a…I tell you, just like you have a good time in the street and all,
Muy duro, porque así uno disfruta en la calle...
But you live from this anyways, so you gotta step up.
Pero de todas maneras de esto vivo. Tengo que continuar.
JALE: The day we don’t work, we don’t earn anything.
El día que no trabajamos, ese día no ganamos nada.
So, we don’t have the joy of taking vacations.
entonces, no tenemos la dicha de darnos vacaciones.
I mean, if we don’t work one thing we have to work the other.
Si no trabajamos en una cosa, tenemos que trabajar en otra.
I wish God gave me the joy of travelling a few days,
Que Dios me diera la dicha de viajar unos días...
seeing other places, seeing other cultures,
conocer otros lugares, otras costumbres...
meeting other salesmen, other people.
conocer otros vendedores, otras personas...
I would be the happiest woman in this world.
Sería la mujer más dichosa de este mundo.
But well, those are things that stay in your thoughts.
Pero bueno, son cosas que se quedan en el pensamiento...
It’s not like it can’t happen, someday it could. Right?
No es que no vaya a suceder... algún día... posiblemente...
But okay, those are dreams, and dreaming doesn’t cost a thing…
Pero bueno eso son sueños... ¡Y como soñar no cuesta nada!